Guide to the Anne X. Alpern Papers, 1918-1974 AIS.2002.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Case Files, 1928-1972 (Bulk 1929-1951); I.
  - Ward v. City of Pittsburgh, et al, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 107 March Term, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Weber v. Weber, County Court of Allegheny County, No. 80, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Weitzel v Metropolitan Life Insurance Co., Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, No. 50 April Term, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Westinghouse Air Brake Co. v. City of Pittsburgh (client), Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 490 July Term, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Williams v. Samuel, et al, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Eastern District, No. 441 January Term, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Various Cases, 1928-1969 (intermittent) (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Professional Files, 1925-1974 (Bulk 1935-1963); II.
  The records in this series represent Alpern's professional career outside the courtroom, notably her service in regulatory agencies such as the Public Parking Authority of the City of Pittsburgh, her participation in professional groups such as the National Institute of Municipal Law Officers (NIMLO), and her advocacy of court reform. The first files hold notebooks kept by Alpern in law school and a file kept by the University of Pittsburgh School of Law tracking Alpern's achievements after graduation.
  Although the correspondence files in this series are not very extensive, they do give a limited view of Alpern's activities and network of acquaintances. Among the correspondents are clients, fellow attorneys, public officials, and citizens who sent in anonymous tips of illegal acts and called for their investigation. This series also holds hand-written notes kept by Alpern, which are often difficult to read.
  A sample of brochures and other promotional material from Alpern's election campaigns in 1953, 1961 and 1963 is followed by documents from Alpern's participation in NIMLO and other agencies. These are arranged in rough chronological order. A script for her presentation to the 1945 meeting of NIMLO concerns the difficulties faced by Pittsburgh city officials in buying war surplus vehicles and other equipment, which she also addressed at the United States Conference of Mayors that same year.
  - Notebooks from Pitt Law School, c1927 (Box 11, Folder 01-02)
  - Student File, 1925-1961 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1929-1972 (intermittent) (Box 12, Folder 02-04)
  - Hand-written Notes: Office, Cases, Speeches, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Letters of Support for Federal Court Campaign, 1948-1949 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Election Campaign Material, 1953-1963 (intermittent) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Legislation Drafts and Notes, c1933-1950 (Box 12, Folder 08-09)
  - United States Conference of Mayors, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - President's Conference on Fire Prevention, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - National Institute of Municipal Law Officers, 1942-1951 (Box 13, Folder 03-06)
  - Public Parking Authority of the City of Pittsburgh, 1948-1951 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Report to Judge William H. McNaugher re: Court Congestion/Backlog, c1953-1958 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 03-05)
  - Official Comments and Statements, 1958, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Other Professional Conferences and Associations, 1950-1973 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Berkman Ruslander Pohl Lieber & Engel Law Firm, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Plaques, Desk Signs and Metal Stamp, 1959-1961 (Oversize 15)
  - Certificates, Awards, Cartoons and Campaign Posters, 1946-1972 (Oversize 1)
- Personal Papers, 1919-1973; III.
  Papers in this series highlight Anne Alpern's activities outside of her professional career, including private pursuits as well as public engagements. Alpern was renowned for her ability to balance a professional career with a home life, and maintained several hobbies as well. At one time she was said to read one non-legal book a day and had a reputation as a gourmet cook, often visiting restaurants and asking for the recipes of dishes she enjoyed. Some recipes obtained from friends, newspapers and other sources are found here, as well as some creative writing by Alpern. This includes an incomplete draft manuscript for a play titled "So Help Me God" and an unnamed short story, both typed and hand-written.
  Alpern was also a popular lecturer. This series holds a small number of programs from her speaking engagements and typescripts or drafts of speeches she gave, which include "The Case against the Courts", a well-known expression of her goals for judicial reform. A few items also pertain to her siblings and her father, Joseph Alpern.
  In 1965, Alpern became involved in the resignation of Chancellor Litchfield from the University of Pittsburgh, eventually writing an article titled "The Big Donor Dropout! What Happened at the University of Pittsburgh." This article is found here together with fairly extensive documentation of the matter, including newspaper clippings.
  - Anne Alpern, 1.
    - Personal Correspondence, 1919-1973 (Box 16, Folder 01-03)
    - Correspondence with Marsha Swiss, 1959-1970 (Box 16, Folder 04-05)
    - Estate of Joseph Alpern, 1937-1973 (intermittent) (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Joseph Alpern Correspondence (in Yiddish), 1928-1930 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Alpern Siblings, 1928-1963 (intermittent) (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Receptions and Social Events, 1939-1974 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - United Jewish Fund of Pittsburgh, Inc., 1947-1949 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - National Jewish Hospital at Denver, 1949-1950 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Hadassah Donor Luncheon, March 27, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - NAACP Human Rights Dinner, March 31, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - American Jewish Committee, 1959 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Speeches, 1941-1958 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Addresses on KQV, 1938, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Address for the League of Women Voters, KDKA, May 20, 1936 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Oakland Renewal Plan, 1962-1963 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - University of Pittsburgh: Chancellor Litchfield's Resignation, 1965-1966 (Box 17, Folder 05-10)
    - Marriage Certificate and Honeymoon Mementos, 1937 (Box 18, Folder 01-02)
    - Creative Writing, undated (Box 18, Folder 03-05)
    - Speeches, Articles and Scripts by Others, c1933-1950 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Personal Interest Newspaper and Journal Clippings, 1950-1970 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Recipes, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Recipes (Oversize 19)
  - Irwin Swiss, c1930-1947; 2.
    Scope and Contents note
    Irwin Swiss, who married Anne Alpern in 1937, was born in Poland in 1897 and moved to Pittsburgh at the age of ten. He worked as an assistant city solicitor for Pittsburgh from 1935 to 1937, and then became a referee of unemployment compensation. In 1943 he joined the legal staff of the Federal Housing Administration, and served with that agency until late 1944, when he was appointed as an assistant United States attorney. In this position he played a prominent role in the prosecution of suspected communist sympathizers. Swiss died in February of 1960 following a traffic accident. These papers include a very limited sample of his correspondence and official papers, newspaper clippings, notebooks and date books. Occasional pages in one of the larger notebooks show handwriting that may be Alpern's.
    Irwin Swiss was a dedicated Zionist and an orator of some reputation. This sub-series contains notes from some of his speeches and a modest selection of articles and notes concerning religious tolerance, anti-Semitism, nationalism and Zionism; poetry and literary criticism; and President Franklin D. Roosevelt's re-election campaign of 1940. Many articles from the Jewish Criterion are included in Box 20, Folder 4.
    - Case File: Hansen Estate, Orphans' Court of Allegheny County, No. 362-A of 1939 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Notes for Speeches and Articles by Irwin Swiss, undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Articles and Notes on Literature and Politics, c1930-1940 (Box 20, Folder 03-08)
    - Positions and Promotions, 1942-1945 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Housing Agencies, 1943-1950 (Box 21, Folder 01-02)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1945 (Intermittent) (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Court and Personal Notebooks, undated (Box 21, Folder 04-07)
    - Pocket Date Books,1919-1947 (Box 22)
    - Certificates of Office and Other Service, 1937-1947 (Intermittent) (Oversize 2)
- Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks, c. 1929-1974; IV.
  These clippings follow Anne Alpern's public career, covering her roles in newsworthy events. Several articles are biographical in focus. There are also many humorous political cartoons commenting on Alpern's role in the workings of the city. Most of these were produced by the local newspaper artist Cy Hungerford in the early 1950s.
  Loose clippings housed in folders are arranged chronologically by year, with some of the years sub-divided by certain topics. A portion of these were sorted and labeled in 1985, and Box 24 holds a typed index to them. This index provides chronological and topical guides, but does not list all of the clippings in this section. The clippings in Box 28, Folder 8 were apparently compiled by someone other than Alpern. They come from newspapers in the Philadelphia region and throughout Pennsylvania, including two Italian newspapers, Il Progresso and Il Popolo. Oversize items include the October 26, 1946 issue of Collier's which featured an article about Alpern, and an article about her 1959 appointment as attorney general.
  Six volumes of scrapbooks complete the series. Volume 1 is from Alpern's senior year in high school and is filled with handwritten messages from classmates. Volumes 2-6 contain newspaper clippings and occasional photographs from the 1940 to 1961. Although they cover many of the same topics, they also contain information not found in the loose clippings.
  - Index and Newspaper Clippings, c1929, 1938-1940 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - 1941-1945 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - 1946 (Box 23, Folder 03-04)
  - Duquesne Light Strike, 1946 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - 1947 (Box 23, Folder 06-07)
  - 1948 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Federal Court Campaign, November 12, 1948-March 18, 1949 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - 1949 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - 1950 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - "Free Work" Probe: Kilgallen and Gross, April 27-June 15, 1950 (Box 24, Folder 05-06)
  - "Free Work" Probe: Kilgallen and Gross, June 16-September 21, 1950 (Box 25, Folder 01-04)
  - 1951 (Box 25, Folder 05-06)
  - January 1951 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - "Free Work" Probe: McCarter, February 9-June 28, 1951 (Box 26, Folder 02-06)
  - "Free Work" Probe: Scrap Selling, March 10-June 13, 1951 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - March 9-June 28, 1951 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - City Contract Probe: Broadway Maintenance Street Lighting, June 9-July 17, 1951 (Box 27, Folder 03-04)
  - 1952 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - 1953 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - 1954-1958 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Appointment as Attorney General, December 24, 1958-1959 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - 1959 (Box 28, Folder 01-03)
  - 1960 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - 1960 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - 1961 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Appointment to Pa. Supreme Court and Campaign, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 01-02)
  - 1963-1974 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Skybus Case, 1972 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified Clippings, undated (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - 1946, 1958-1959 (Oversize 3)
  - High School Senior Year, 1918-1919 (Oversize 3, Volume 1)
  - 1940-1945 (Oversize 3, Volume 2)
  - 6th Annual National Newspaper Dinner, Scranton Elks, 1956 (Oversize 3, Volume 3)
  - 1959 (Oversize 3, Volume 4)
  - 1959-1961 (Oversize 3, Volume 5)
  - 1961 (Oversize 3, Volume 6)
- Photographs, V.
  Professional photographs include portraits and shots of Anne Alpern with other attorneys and political officials, including David L. Lawrence, Genevieve Blatt, and Eleanor Roosevelt. Most of the photographs appear to have been taken in or near Pittsburgh. Personal photographs include vacation snapshots and pictures of Alpern's family and friends. Oversize photographs show Alpern with David Lawrence and other political officials, members of NIMLO, and Alpern's family.
  - Early Photographs: Family, School (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Portraits (Box 30, Folder 02-03)
  - Professional (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Family of Anne Alpern, Irwin Swiss, and Marsha Swiss (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Vacations (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Extended Family and Friends (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Oversize Photos (Oversize 4)
- Closed Files, VI.
  Scope and Contents Notes
  These files contain information that is or may be protected by the attorney-client privilege. In order to ensure compliance with regulations regarding the privilege, they are closed until further notice.
  - Ahrle (Immigration to U.S.) [RESTRICTED], 1940-1941 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Allison v. Allison, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, Docket "D", No. 3016 April Term [RESTRICTED], 1939 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Alpern v. National Association of Women's and Children's Apparel Salesmen, Inc. (NAWCAS) Benevolent Auxiliary [RESTRICTED], 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Basic Foods, Inc. v. Moyer, United States District Court for the Western District of Pennsylvania, Civil Action No. 2947 [RESTRICTED], 1940-1944 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Baysoi v. Jessop Steel Co., United States District Court of the United States for the Western District of Pennsylvania, Civil Action No. 7963 [RESTRICTED], 1949-1950 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Berg Wills, Property [RESTRICTED], 1939, 1951, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Blank v. Blank, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 756 January Term 1950-D [RESTRICTED], 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Brandt v. Hoffman, No. 2016 July Term [RESTRICTED], 1935 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Commonwealth v. C.I.T. Corporation (Motors Mortgage Corp.), Court of Common Pleas of Dauphin County, Commonwealth Docket, 1928; No. 113 Commonwealth Docket, 1929; Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Middle District, No. 9 May Term, 1929 [RESTRICTED], 1928-1929 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Commonwealth ex rel. Fidelity Trust Co. v. Babcock (client), Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 2273 October Term, 1934 [RESTRICTED], 1934-1949 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Cunningham Estate [RESTRICTED], 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Davis Release to Truco, Inc. [RESTRICTED], 1947-1948 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Dixon v. Dixon, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 2111 January Term, 1937 [RESTRICTED], 1936-1937 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Dorian, U.S. Citizenship [RESTRICTED], 1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Failla v. Paulo [RESTRICTED], 1950-1951 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Fisher v. Fisher, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 3349 July Term, 1936 [RESTRICTED], 1936-1937 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Gamble Estate [RESTRICTED], 1929-1944 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Hahn v. Hively (client) [RESTRICTED], 1938 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Hamilton v. Hamilton, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 938, 1925; No. 1389 January Term, 1938 [RESTRICTED], 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Handelman [RESTRICTED], 1934 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Howell Divorce [RESTRICTED], 1948 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Hughes Patent [RESTRICTED], 1951 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Kerr Estate, Orphans' Court of Allegheny County, No. 539 September Term, 1935; Kerr v. Kerr, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 2452 July Term, 1936 [RESTRICTED], 1935-1941 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - King v. King, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 1960 October Term, 1949 [RESTRICTED], 1949-1951 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Kline Estate, Orphans' Court of Westmoreland Co. and Superior Court of Pa. Sitting at Pittsburgh, No. 141 April Term, 1947 [RESTRICTED], 1947-1950 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Koontz v. Lescallet, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 962 April Term, 1939 [RESTRICTED], 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Malone Divorce [RESTRICTED], c1932 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - McIntire Estate [RESTRICTED], 1934 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Moore Estate [RESTRICTED], 1950 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Mulford, Separation and Trust Agreements [RESTRICTED], 1931-1936 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Pellegrini, Various Claims [RESTRICTED], 1943-1950 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Pellegrini, v. Radiant Society, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 999 October Term, 1940 [RESTRICTED], 1940-1943 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad Slide Case [RESTRICTED], 1938 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - In re: Perfect Laundries of Pittsburgh, Inc., District Court of the United States, Western District of Pennsylvania, No. 16726 in Bankruptcy [RESTRICTED], 1931 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Pillmore v. Pillmore [RESTRICTED], 1936-1939 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Potts Estate, Orphans' Court of Philadelphia County, No. 189 of 1938 [RESTRICTED] (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Rosen Divorce [RESTRICTED], 1945-1947 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - In Re. Ryan Estate, Orphans' Court of Allegheny County, Docket 51, c1936; County of Allegheny v. Ryan, et al, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, Lev. Fa. No. 525 July Term, 1949, Sur. Judgment Sci. Fa. No. 3353 April Term, 1949 [RESTRICTED], 1929-1949 (intermittent) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - In Re. Schmitt [RESTRICTED], 1951 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Schoen & Schoen v. Elsasser, Court of Common Pleas of Somerset County, No. 566 September Term, 1931, C.D.; Elsasser v. Schoen, Court of Common Pleas of Somerset County, No. 3 February Term, 1932, C.D. [RESTRICTED], 1931-1932, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Shields v. Shields, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 2706 April Term [RESTRICTED], 1948 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Sieg v. Sieg, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 1828 October Term, 1939 [RESTRICTED], 1939-1942 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Sutton, Stock Sale [RESTRICTED], 1949 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Travis v. Travis, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 1858 April Term, 1949 [RESTRICTED], 1949-1950 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Wall v. Wall, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 2747 April Term, 1949B [RESTRICTED], 1948-1949 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Williams v. Baskerville (client), Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, No. 1977 July Term, 1936 [RESTRICTED], 1936-1938 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Young [RESTRICTED], 1944-1949 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Various Cases [RESTRICTED], 1933-1970 (intermittent) (Box 10, Folder 17)